Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Edgar Hatcher Papers, 1952-1992 RL.00707
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Edgar Hatcher papers
1952-1992
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00707
4.5 Linear Feet
250 Items
Access Restrictions
Access to some portions of the Edgar Hatcher Papers are restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Edgar Hatcher Papers were transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1992.
Biographical Note
Chronology
1927, Jan. 20 Born in High Point, North Carolina
1943 Entered North Carolina State to study engineering
1944 Entered the Navy V-5 program at Duke University, attended pre-flight school in Chapel Hill, NC
1945, Fall Returned to Duke University to study English
1947 Received AB in English, Duke University, Durham, NC
1947-1948 Moved to New York, where he roomed with Duke classmate William Styron who was writing Lie Down in Darkness at the time
1948-1949 Worked at theVick Chemical Company as a sales and advertising trainee selling Vick's VapoRub throughout the Midwest and South
1949-1950 Joined Young and Rubicam in the mail room and later in the research department
1950-1951 Became a Copywriter at Deutsch and Shea
1951, Feb. 22 Married Barbara
1951-1957 Joined G.M. Basford Co. as Creative Group Supervisor,working with the following clients: General Electric, Air Reduction Co., Chemical Manufacturer's Association
1958-1960 Became a Account Supervisor at Benton and Bowles, client: IBM
1960-1966 Joined Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather as Creative Supervisor working on the Shell Oil and Maxim Freeze Dried Coffee accounts
1966-1967 Worked as Creative Group Head at Kenyon and Eckhardt, on the Ford Corporate and Ford Lincoln Mercury Division account
1968-1970 Batten, Barton, Durstine, and Osborn's San Francisco office as Creative Group Manager for the Chevron Oil account
1970-1976 Became Vice President, Associate Creative Director at McCann-Erickson for the following accounts: Exxon/Esso, Campbell's Soup, Ad Council, National Council on Productivity and Quality of Working Life, Savings and Loan Foundation, Bahamas
1976-1981 Became Vice President, Associate Creative Director, Copy Group Head at J. Walter Thompson for the Eastman Kodak, Ford, and STP Corporation accounts
1981-1992 Rejoined McCann-Erickson as Vice President Associate Creative Director for the Beechcraft, Exxon, Texas Instruments accounts
1992, March 1 Retired from McCann-Erickson
Edgar Hatcher and his wife Barbara have two children, Edgar A. Hatcher IV and Liza Hatcher Dawson, both of whom also attended Duke University. The Hatchers live in New York.
Collection Overview
The Edgar Hatcher Papers, 1952-1992, document Hatcher's career as a copywriter and creative director for several major advertising agencies, including G.M. Basford Co.; Benton and Bowles; Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather; Kenyon and Eckhardt; Batten, Barton, Durstine, and Osborn's San Francisco office; McCann-Erickson; and J. Walter Thompson Company. The collection provides an overview into oil company advertising and the development of advertising in several firms from the 1950s through the early 1990s. Materials include reports, correspondence, memoranda, scripts, storyboards, collateral literature, notes, photographs, audio and video tapes, films, and cassette recordings which document the creative development of print, radio and television advertising for various clients. Clients represented include General Electric, Air Reduction Co., Chemical Manufacturer's Association, IBM, Shell Oil, Maxim Freeze Dried Coffee, Ford and Lincoln Mercury, Chevron Oil, Exxon/Esso, Campbell's Soup, Advertising Council, National Council on Productivity and Quality of Working Life, Savings and Loan Foundation, Eastman Kodak, and Beechcraft.
The Clients Series focuses on Hatcher's work on radio and television advertising campaigns, and include many scripts for commercials in various stages of development. Of particular note are materials documenting campaigns for oil companies during the 1960s and 1970s, including Chevon, Shell and Exxon. Included is documentation of the award winning TV commercial for Super Shell Platformate Gasoline entitled Railroad Mileage from 1964 in which a car smashes through a paper sign. Included is significant documentation of advertising from 1968-1970 for Chevron's F-310 gasoline and materials relating to advertising for Exxon during the energy crisis in 1974-1975. Also included in this series are materials relating to Hatcher's creation of the famous Ford has a Better Idea campaign in 1966 and Hatcher's development of the Efficiency of Quality campaign for Beechcraft airplanes in the 1980s.
The Audio Visual Series contains recordings of interviews Hatcher conducted with several noted film makers between 1978-1980 for an Eastman Kodak campaign. Film makers interviewed include Margaret Booth, Joel Chaseman, Mike Cimino, Richard Donner, Blake Edwards, Bill Evans, Bob Gaffney, Art Ornitz, Aaron Spelling, Jimmy Stewart, Grant Tinker, and King Vidor. Also in this series are recordings of radio commercials with which Hatcher was involved such as Campbell's Soup is Good Food campaign for which Hatcher wrote the lyrics and copy. Also included are video tapes and films of television commerials created by Hatcher.
The Advertisements Series contains print advertisements for campaigns on which Hatcher worked. The Chevron F-310 and the Beechcraft Efficiency of Quality campaigns are best represented. A 1955 Chemical Manufacturer's Association ad features the Hatcher family in High Point, NC.
J. Walter Thompson Company
- Clients, 1952-1992and undated,bulk 1960-1975.
  Scope and Contents note
  This series consists of reports, memoranda, scripts, storyboards, collateral literature, rough drafts, notes, and photographs related to the creative development of advertising campaigns. An Information Folder found at the beginning of the series contains biographical information on Hatcher and his personal notes of his thoughts and experiences with serveral client's accounts on which he worked.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged alphabetically by client, noting advertising agency. See Advertisements Series for print advertisements and the Audio Visual Series for radio and televion advertisements.
  - Information Folder, 1977, 1992 (Box 1)
  - Ad Council, National Center for Productivity and Quality of Working Life ( McCann-Erickson):
    - Photoboard of commercial written by Nelson Rockefeller, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Beechcraft ( McCann-Erickson):
    - Campaign development, 1991-1992 (Box 1)
    - Collateral literature, 1983-1987and undated, two folders (Box 1)
    - Houston meetings with Beechcraft executives, 1983-1990 (Box 1)
    - King Air Fact Book, (reference for account people), 1982, Nov. 19 (Box 1)
  - Chevron ( Batten, Barton, Durstine, and Osborn - San Francisco):
    - F-310, campaign development, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Radio Scripts, 1969 (Box 1)
    - Storyboards for F-310 ads, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
    - Four Focus Group Interviews on a Positioning Concept for a New Anti-Pollutant Additive, 1969, Feb. 21 (Box 1)
  - Chevron (Batten, Barton, Durstine, and Osborn - San Francisco): (Box 2)
    - Top-Line Summary of Results of F-310 Study, 1969, April 28 (Box 2)
    - A Study to Determine the Most Effective Creative Approach for Advertising F-310, 1969, May 8 (Box 2)
    - Program Planning Guide for F-310, 1969 (Box 2)
    - A Study of the Effectiveness of the 1970 F-310 Campaign, 1970, April 30 (Box 2)
    - Vol. I, “Tracking the F-310 Campaign in Southern California” (Box 2)
    - Vol. II, “ Public Reactions to Specific Television Commercials” (Box 2)
    - Vol. III, “Tracking the F-310 Campaign in Five Major WOI Markets: San Francisco, Sacramento, Seattle, Portland, and Phoenix” (Box 2)
  - Exxon/Esso ( McCann-Erickson):
    - Copy for print ads, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Draft of proposed booklet about oil well off Florida coast, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Public relations campaign during energy crisis, 1974 (Box 2)
    - Storyboards, undated (Box 2)
  - Exxon/Esso (McCann-Erickson): (Box 2)
    - Translations of Japanese Esso commercials, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
    - TV scripts, 1974-1975 (Box 2)
    - Fairmont Railway Motors (Box 2)
    - First draft of 120 second commercial, undated (Box 2)
  - Ford (Kenyon and Eckhardt): (Box 3)
    - “ Ford Has a Better Idea” campaign development, 1966-1968 (Box 3)
    - Mercury, rough ads and copy, 1966-1967 (Box 3)
  - Ford (J. Walter Thompson Company):
    - Philippines, 1980 (Box 3)
  - Ford (unidentified agency):
    - Compilation of Ford car photos from earliest to 1971 Mustang, undated (Box 3)
  - General Electric ( G.M. Basford Co.):
    - Defense Campaign, 1953-1955 (Box 3)
    - Collateral Literature, 1952-1954 (Box 3)
    - Subcontracting Campaign, 1952-1953 (Box 3)
    - A Report on What Official Washington Thinks about the General Electric Small Business Advertising Program, 1953, Aug. 10 (Box 3)
    - G.M. Basford Co. (Box 3)
    - House ad featuring Hatcher, undated (Box 3)
  - IBM (Benton and Bowles):
    - “Product Image for TINY,” 1959 (Box 3)
    - Maxim Freeze Dried Coffee (Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather) (Box 3)
    - Test Marketing scripts, 1965 (Box 3)
  - Shell ( Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather):
    - Campaign development, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - Radio scripts, 1964and undated (Box 3)
    - TV scripts and storyboards, 1960-1965 (Box 3)
    - Railroad Mileage commercial, 2nd prize Cannes International Advertising Film Festival, The Flagbearer newsletter, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Composition of Shell Gasoline for Motor Cars, undated (Box 3)
  - Texas Instruments ( McCann-Erickson):
    - Disk, Design For Test, Demo, 1990 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1962-1992.
  Materials include a report, a letter to and one from David Ogilvy commenting on a speech Ogilvy gave to the American Association of Advertising Agencies, two speeches Hatcher gave to two universities as a representative of the Advertising Education Foundation, and writings on telegraphic copy style and copy practices at McCann Erickson.
  Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Copy Research Methods Utilized at Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather, 1962 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with David Ogilvy, 1991-1992 (Box 3)
  - Speeches and Comments on Copywriting, 1987-1991 (Box 3)
- Advertisements Series, 1952-1987
  Series contains print advertisements and oversize collateral literature.
  Arranged alphabetically by client.
  - Air Reduction Company (G.M. Basford Co.), Corporate Campaign, 1950s (Box 4)
  - Beechcraft (McCann-Erickson), 1983-1987 (Box 4)
  - Chevron (BBDO- San Francisco), 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Exxon/Esso (McCann-Erickson), 1975, undated (Box 4)
  - Ford (Kenyon and Eckhardt), original “ Ford Has a Better Idea” ad, 1966 (Box 4)
  - General Electric (G.M. Basford Co.) (Box 4)
  - Defense campaign, collateral literature, 1952-1954 (Box 4)
  - Apparatus, electrical equipment, 1955-1957 (Box 4)
  - Subcontracting campaign, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - Subcontracting campaign, collateral literature, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
  - IBM (Benton and Bowles), 1958-1960 (Box 4)
  - Shell (Ogilvy, Benson, and Mather), 1960-1965 (Box 4)
- Audio Visual Series, 1966-1991
  Conditions Governing Access note
  Access is RESTRICTED to film and non-VHS video formats.
  Series contains cassette tapes, reel to reel tapes, VHS and other video formats, 8 and 16 mm films.
  Arranged by format, then alphabetically by client within formats.
  - Audio cassette tapes: (Box 5)
    - Eastman Kodak (J. Walter Thompson Company) (Box 5)
    - Interviews by Edgar Hatcher with noted film makers for Eastman Kodak producers campaign, 1978-1980 (Box 5)
    - Booth, Margaret, movie editor, 1978, Dec. 6 (Box 5)
    - Chaseman, Joel, Washington Post TV station, 1978, Nov. 6 (Box 5)
    - Cimino, Mike, 1980, Feb. 14(2 tapes) (Box 5)
    - Donner, Richard, 1979, June 27 (Box 5)
    - Edwards, Blake, 1978, Sept. 26 (Box 5)
    - Evans, Bill, Clio Awards, 1978, March 1 (Box 5)
    - Gaffney, Bob, 1979, Jan. 24 (Box 5)
    - Spelling, Aaron, 1978, Dec. 4 (Box 5)
    - Stewart, Jimmy. undated (Box 5)
    - Tinker, Grant, 1980, March 14 (two tapes) (Box 5)
    - Ornitz, Art, 1979, Feb. 23[side a of second Tinker tape] (Box 5)
    - Vidor, King, 1978, May 8 (Box 5)
  - Audio reel to reel tapes: (Box 6)
    - Campbell's Soup, (McCann-Erickson)“Soup is Good Food” and “Comin' Home” commercials, 1975, Dec. 4 (Box 6)
    - Exxon/Esso (McCann-Erickson) (Box 6)
    - Esso Caribbean, “The Tiger Never Sleeps,” English and Spanish commercials, undated (Box 6)
    - 8 Esso spots, undated (Box 6)
    - Esso “Hesitation” radio jingle, undated (Box 6)
    - Exxon, “A Couple of Fairy Tales on Behalf of Exxon,” “Princess” and “Knight,” with Peter Thomas and Paul Evans, 1973, March 28 (Box 6)
    - Ford (Kenyon and Eckhardt) (Box 6)
    - 30 second radio spots, 1966, May 20 (Box 6)
  - Video Tapes - VHS Format
    - Ad Council, National Council on Productivity and Quality of Working Life (McCann-Erickson), “Sign Your Work,” 1976 (Box 6)
    - 19 commercials, mostly McCann-Erickson for Advertising Education Foundation presentation, Franklin and Marshall, 1990, Nov. 12,clients include: SOS, Tipanillo, Kleenex, Jello, Coca-Cola, Esso, Nescafe, Oreo, Freia, ATandT, PGandE, Isuzu, Milk, Johnson and Johnson [see list in tape box for names of commercials] (Box 6)
  - Video Tapes for which access is restricted: (Box 7)
    - U-matic video tape, television commercials (Box 7)
    - Ford Granada, “Pretty Face” and “Rough Roads” (Box 7)
    - Campbell's Soup, “Soup is Good Food” (Box 7)
    - Ad Council, National Council on Productivity (Box 7)
    - Kodak, “Baby Face” (Box 7)
    - Absorbine, “Rote” (Box 7)
    - Exxon, “American Worker,” 1976 (Box 7)
    - Ford, 3 original “Ford Has a Better Idea” 20 second spots (Box 7)
    - Esso jingle (Box 7)
    - Shell, first demo of car going through sign, 120 seconds (Box 7)
    - Video tape, commercials by Ed Hatcher, 34 spots, clients include: Exxon/Esso, Ad Council's National Council on Productivity, Shell, Chevron, OIC, Campbell's Soup, and Ford, 1960-1976[see list inside tape] (Box 7)
    - Video tape, Exxon, (McCann-Erickson, Houston) “ Exxon- 75 Years of Achievement,” undated (Box 7)
    - Video tape, McCann-Erickson international show reel, clients include: SOS, Wells Fargo, Hamburger Bendblatt, R-Kisoki, Levi's, Quilmes Beer, Goodyear, Friends of Earth, Nescafe, Maggi, GM, Banco Lottery, Isuzu, Coca-Cola, Johnson and Johnson, Raymond, Nestles, Nipi, Comtech, 1991, Dec.[see list inside tape] (Box 7)
  - Films, access is restricted
    - 8mm, Savings and Loan Foundation, (McCann-Erickson) “IRA Watch,” “Young Family,” “Social Security,” undated,(3 films) (Box 7)
    - 16mm, unidentified (Box 7)
- Oversize Materials
  - Advertisements Series
    - Beechcraft (McCann-Erickson), 1983-1987 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Chemical Manufacturer's Association (G.M. Basford Co.), 1955 (Oversize-box 1)
    - IBM (Benton and Bowles), 1958-1960 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Air Reduction Company (G.M. Basford), 1950s (Oversize-box 1)
    - Chevron (BBDO- San Francisco), 1968-1970 (Oversize-box 1)
    - Ford Lincoln Mercury (Kenyon and Eckhardt), 1967 (Oversize-box 1)
    - General Electric (G.M. Basford), 1952-1957 (Oversize-box 1)